A few months
after the execution of Arcadio,
Colonel Aureliano Buendía was captured
just before he reached the border
of the western frontier.
Of the 21 men who followed him to war,
only one survived,
Colonel Gerineldo Márquez.
-What happened to your hand?
-Nothing. It's just a burn.
Aureliano José's all grown up now.
Get back.
-Aureliano!
-Get back.
-I said get back.
-Where's Magnífico? Huh?
-Where is our son?
-Where is he?
-Get back.
-Don't touch me!
-Get back!
-Hands off! Hands off!
-Go home, Mother!
Ask the authorities for permission,
and come visit me in jail!
Aureliano!
Let go!
Long live Colonel Buendía!
-That's enough!
-Aureliano!
The party's over now!
There's nothing to see here! Let's go!
Everybody back to your homes!
Colonel Aureliano Buendía's
sentence would be carried out in Macondo
as a lesson to the people.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
Ma'am. Ma'am!
I need to see
Colonel Aureliano Buendía. My son.
-Let me in.
-Ma'am!
-Captain! I said let me in!
-Get back now!
She can come in!
I want to see my son,
Colonel Aureliano Buendía.
Sorry,
are you referring to "Mister" Buendía?
Whatever you say.
Just let me see Aureliano.
We're just waiting for the government
to ratify his official sentence.
What sentence?
The death penalty.
Meanwhile,
he's to stay in complete isolation.
There's no way I'm not seeing my son.
I'm going inside, so shoot me
if that's the order you were given.
Take her.
I haven't told you this,
but Arcadio named his baby Remedios.
He wanted to name her Úrsula, but
that name comes with great suffering.
You never told me any of this.
But I already knew.
You were born with your eyes wide open…
looking all around…
so curious yet so unbothered.
I haven't forgotten that.
And I haven't forgotten
the sadness in your face…
…when you saw me return
without your brother…
after I left you and Amaranta behind.
That image of you still breaks my heart.
I feel like I've already
lived through all of this.
But I can't see my own death.
As if the omens have abandoned me
for some reason.
I have something for you.
These are the poems I wrote for Remedios.
Promise me…
that you'll burn them.
I don't want anyone to read them.
Time's up! Let's go!
Don't say goodbye.
Don't beg anyone
or humiliate yourself for me.
This is a war.
Instead, you should act
as if I was executed ages ago.
Interested in having
a bit of fun tonight, Captain?
Good evening.
So you know, sir,
we didn't come here after anyone.
My fellow officers and I
simply want a drink
and to have a good time.
No one wants to lie with
a man on death row, Captain Carnicero.
It's bad luck.
The only ones on death row are the rebels.
Maybe.
But the whole town knows
that the officer who executes
Colonel Aureliano Buendía,
as well as every soldier in his platoon,
one by one…
will be killed sooner or later,
without exception.
Even if they run
to the far corners of the earth.
Well…
Look, I have nothing against the colonel.
In fact, I admire his bravery.
But, unfortunately, if we are ordered to,
we'll be forced to execute him.
That is our duty.
Pray then.
Pray that you never receive that order.
Pardon me, Captain.
That it?
Gerineldo Márquez…
you've been sentenced
to spend seven years in prison.
It looks like
you and I weren't as fortunate.
You have been sentenced
to death for rebellion.
The telegram orders your execution
to take place immediately.
That's truly wonderful news.
We have our first telegraph in Macondo.
He did not
feel fear or nostalgia,
but rage at the thought
that his artful death
would not allow him to see the end
of the many things he had left unfinished.
Any last words, Colonel Buendía?
As he faced the firing squad,
Colonel Aureliano Buendía
was to remember that distant afternoon
when his father took him to discover ice.
He saw himself again as a child
wearing short pants
and a tie around his neck.
And he thought of José Arcadio Buendía,
who at that moment was thinking about him,
under the somber dawn
of the chestnut tree.
Soldiers.
Prepare.
Aim your guns.
Hold your fire.
Soldiers,
put down your weapons.
You were sent here by Divine Providence.
Release him!
Just do it!
I'm at your service, Colonel Buendía.
Welcome to the revolution, Carnicero.
So, I guess it turns out
that you're Divine Providence.
Hmm.
Well, don't you think someone
had to come rescue you?
-Hmm.
-Don't get yourself killed again.
I won't save you, Aureliano.
No one ever learned
of his involvement
in halting the execution.
Captain Roque Carnicero and his men
left town with Colonel Aureliano Buendía,
and they joined the revolutionary forces
of Colonel Victoriano Medina.
One year after
Colonel Aureliano Buendía's escape,
the Buendía residence
was once again filled with children.
Úrsula had taken in
Santa Sofía de la Piedad
and her eldest daughter, Remedios…
How many times
have I told you not to do that?
…and a pair of twins who were born
after the execution of their father,
named Aureliano Segundo
and José Arcadio Segundo.
"Sa-tur-day."
"Tha-tur-day."
Let's try that again.
Amaranta took care of them all.
This one?
Listen to this.
"After many years of confrontations,
the government will meet
for the first time
with liberal politicians to discuss
the terms of a potential truce."
Hmm.
You saw it coming, José Arcadio.
You never needed an omen to tell you
that politics are nothing but a plague.
-…Thursday.
-Good job.
Good morning!
It's a bowl!
Where's the rest?
My sons are fighting
for the Liberals in the countryside.
With your brother, Colonel Buendía.
What's that got to do with anything?
Well… it's just the two of us,
and we can't take care
of the whole harvest ourselves.
I'm asking you to give me more time, sir.
Tell them to come work
and stop playing soldiers.
Does it hurt?
Yeah.
-Auntie?
-Mm-hmm?
Please can I sleep with you tonight?
Aureliano José,
you need to get used to sleeping alone.
It's the last time. I promise you.
All right.
Tired of living among the dead,
José Arcadio and Rebeca moved
to the house built by Arcadio.
They made it their home,
and continued to love each other freely.
Mm.
All right, let's go again.
Three times three?
-Three times three…
-Think about it.
-Nine!
-Five times two…
Rebeca maintained
that she hadn't seen anything.
It was difficult to believe,
but no other story was more plausible,
as no one could conceive a reason
why she would murder the man
that had made her happy.
That was perhaps the only mystery
in Macondo that was never solved.
Rebeca shut the doors of her house
and buried herself alive,
covered with a thick crust of disdain
that no earthly temptation
was ever able to break.
Colonel,
they're waiting for us. Are you all right?
I was thinking about my brother.
Now I know why, for the last two nights,
I've dreamt of him.
You've all been summoned
as the regional leaders you are,
to show your support for the Liberal Party
in a crucial day for our country!
The Conservative government…
is now open to dialogue.
And we must answer their call!
We should be answering with gunpowder!
-That's right!
-Yeah!
Everyone, settle down,
settle down, settle down! Please!
Try to understand
that the absolute best way to end this war
is to reach a consensus.
What consensus is that, huh?
Well,
whatever consensus is necessary.
First, we must go to the capital
so we can--
For example, to begin with,
the representation
of Liberals in Congress is fundamental
as well as in other government offices.
That is what all of you want!
Yeah!
The future of Colombia
is what's at stake, all right?
And to reach a negotiation,
we need to stop fighting.
-Like hell we're gonna stop fighting now!
-What is wrong with these guys?
Have you no sense? Come on!
What's really at stake right now…
Carry on like this!
…is the dignity of our people.
And you cannot negotiate that.
If you sign in favor of an armistice,
we may be able to demand participation
in the regional elections…
…for you, sir.
That's right.
Sign here, Colonel.
We'll sign that
when there is more
to offer to the Liberals.
But until then,
we will continue with our fight.
That's right.
Stop.
For your support
of the Liberal insurgency…
-Hey, I said get back!
-Please, sir, I beg you! Please!
The Colombian Government
sentences you to death!
Prepare!
Aim!
Long live the Liberal Party!
Uh!
That is how the legend
of Colonel Aureliano Buendía was born.
Long live Coronel Buendía!
Buendía!
HUICÁN'S TOWN HALL
Over the following years,
the colonel armed
more than one thousand men,
and he declared total war
against the government.
Long live the revolution.
Uh!
-Ah!
Colonel.
What do you mean? I told you guys
you could have those two, okay?
I thought you'd be interested.
Ah, well, I'll drink to that.
This is how they thank us
for leaving our blood on the battlefield.
WANTED, DEAD OR ALIVE
Hmm.
If the Liberals are gonna kneel
to those Conservative sons of bitches…
then we're going after them as well.
-May I come in, Colonel?
-Yes, come in.
You wanna kill me, you son of a bitch?
Ah!
And so, another war began.
Here, sir.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía's men
proclaimed him
Chief of the Revolutionary Forces
of the Caribbean,
ranking him as General.
Although he assumed the position,
he would not accept the promotion
until every member
of the Conservative regime
was removed from power.
Ah!
Colonel.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía.
General José Raquel Moncada.
All politicians are
complete shit, Moncada.
The only difference is,
Liberals go to mass at five o'clock,
and Conservatives go to mass at 8:00.
You're right.
Which is why this war
is completely futile.
Other Liberal leaders have already started
negotiating with the government.
And they're about to sign, Aureliano.
Everyone is worn out.
It's been over ten years.
And we'll fight for ten more
or however long we have to
for our people to decide their fate.
We've been muzzled for long enough,
and we're done.
We both know that you wanna keep fighting
to get even
for what your own party did to you.
That's true.
I won't deny it.
All of those Liberal leaders
need to understand
that our army is legitimate.
Don't confuse our men with bandits.
Then stop attacking
innocent civilians, Aureliano.
You have enemies everywhere now.
Then why are you here, Moncada?
Did they send you here to bribe me?
Or to intimidate me?
Nobody sent me to do anything.
I just came to say goodbye
because I quit the fight.
I've been appointed
civil and military chief of Macondo.
I will look after your town.
That, I can promise you.
You're one of the most decent men
I've ever known, José Raquel.
But unfortunately,
you're still a Conservative.
Breakfast is served!
Aureliano Segundo! José Arcadio Segundo!
The twins were so similar
and mischievous,
neither their own mother nor grandmother
could tell them apart.
-Good morning, Grandma.
Morning.
Sit over there, Aureliano Segundo.
Aureliano José.
Aureliano José!
Just like his father had
at his age,
Aureliano José
had quickly grown into a man.
Yes, Grandma?
Go get Remedios and your Aunt Amaranta.
Their food is starting to get cold.
Aureliano José felt
a strange trembling
at the sight of her splendid breasts
with their brown nipples.
He continued to study her,
discovering the miracle of
her intimacy inch by inch,
and he felt his skin tingle
as he regarded her.
Good afternoon.
Are you Úrsula Iguarán de Buendía?
-Yes.
-Ma'am.
General José Raquel Moncada.
At your service.
How can I help you?
I've been appointed the new
civil and military chief of Macondo.
And it would be
a very special honor for me
if you would assist me, Mrs. Buendía,
in showing me around.
The military forces have caused
a lot of damage to Macondo, General.
Both the red and the blue.
I know that.
And my mission is to care for the people,
despite the color of their banners.
I promised Colonel Buendía.
Have you talked to my son?
I have.
I met with him before coming here.
Was he captured?
No, he's with his troop,
leading the revolutionary army.
He's my enemy though.
Close enemy.
But we have one common enemy
that we hate even more each other.
Injustice.
Injustice is constantly swaying
in the direction of what's convenient.
These days,
words are as empty as they were
back in the time of the insomnia plague.
Mrs. Buendía,
I respect your son,
and I intend to treat Macondo
with the same respect.
That much I can promise you.
Well, I hope you will, General.
Macondo can't bleed anymore
for this endless war.
Have a nice afternoon.
-I didn't hear you.
-My apologies.
Amaranta?
-Hmm?
-Where are the candles?
J… just a second. I… I'll get them.
It's all right. She didn't see us.
Not today,
but if we keep this up, she will.
Mother! Here they are.
While Colonel Aureliano Buendía
snuck around the narrow trails
of permanent subversion,
General Moncada replaced soldiers
with unarmed policemen,
hoping to foster a trusting environment.
One that made people think of the war
as an absurd nightmare of the past.
No banner should ever be above
the dignity of a human being.
That's why the people of Macondo
should all share the same rights.
The same opportunities.
That's always been its founders' wishes.
And the very first step
to make it a reality
is guaranteeing public education.
So, as of today,
this space will serve
its original purpose once again.
I have to be honest,
I didn't think you'd keep your promise
or that I would live to see
the Macondo I knew
from the time of José Arcadio again.
What was it like back then?
There were no sides,
no soldiers.
We had no idea what fear was.
And people painted their houses
the way they saw fit.
Well, I'm glad to hear
that we're on the right path.
Yes.
Any news on Aureliano?
No.
I just hope he's considering
surrendering his weapons.
Eventually, men get accustomed to war…
until they can't find their
way out of it again.
I'm your aunt.
What we're doing is awful.
No, it's not. It's beautiful.
Get out.
Don't you realize what we're doing?
This is forbidden.
Leave me be. Please go.
Is that what you really want?
Tell me to leave you alone again,
and I swear I will.
I want you to go as far away as you can.
Then I'd rather go
and be killed in the trenches.
It'd be better than your indifference.
Where's your grandfather?
He's right here.
He's been this way all morning.
We've just received a letter.
It's Aureliano.
He says his omens have returned.
We come from water.
ÚRSULA, MOM,
TAKE GREAT CARE OF DAD
BECAUSE HE IS GOING TO DIE.
AURELIANO B.
In spite of
his undiminished strength,
José Arcadio Buendía
was in no condition to fight.
That colossal old man,
beaten by the sun and rain,
was indifferent to everything.
We come from water,
and our fates are intertwined.
Try to sleep some, my love.
The afternoon is so beautiful
and cool.
Wait, woman!
Wait, I'm not sleepy yet.
José Arcadio Buendía found
consolation in dreaming of infinite rooms.
He dreamt of getting out of bed,
opening the door,
and entering another room,
My dear boy.
Melquiades,
my dear old friend.
And then another,
as if in a gallery of mirrors,
until he came across a descendant of his,
Aureliano Babilonia,
as he read, many years later,
from Melquiades's manuscripts,
about that very same moment
José Arcadio Buendía was living.
Prudencio.
A light rain
of tiny, yellow flowers
fell over the town
all through the night in a silent storm.
They covered the roofs
and blocked the doors.
So many flowers fell from the sky
that they had to
clear the streets away with shovels
so the funeral procession
could pass through.
Years
after the death of his father,
at dawn on the first of October,
Colonel Aureliano Buendía
returned to Macondo
with one thousand well-armed men.
The garrison had received orders
to resist to the end.
Ladies! Gentlemen!
Please go home!
Everyone, close your doors! Stay inside!
Come on! Keep moving!
Bring that cannon to the front!
Very good!
José Raquel!
José Raquel, what's happening?
Aureliano.
He and his men arrived at dawn.
What will you do?
If they attack us,
we will defend ourselves.
Bring the machine gun here!
To the front as well! Everyone ready?
I don't know which one of you
is the bigger fool here!
PUBLIC SCHOOL
Úrsula felt like
her son was a stranger.
His face had acquired a metallic hardness,
and he was showing the first symptoms
of resistance to nostalgia.
Aureliano.
Mother.
Will you attack Macondo?
That'd be an atrocity.
There is no other way.
We have to overthrow the government.
Aureliano, my God.
We have had so many years of tranquility.
No one has spoken of parties or banners.
Don't do this, son.
I'll give Moncada the option to surrender.
That's more than enough, I think.
You are the leader of these bandits,
aren't you?
You're able to decide
whether or not the war returns to Macondo!
Do you know how long
I have waited for the moment
that I could finally
take back Macondo for our cause?
No, I don't.
But I do know this much.
There is still time
for you to do what is right.
VICTORY WILL BE FOUND IN THE FRAY
Faithful departed.
God the Son,
Redeemer of the world, have mercy
on the souls of the faithful departed.
God the Holy Ghost…
have mercy on the souls
of the faithful departed.
Thou who holdest the keys,
Holy Trinity,
have mercy on the souls
of the faithful departed.
Holy Trinity, one God, have mercy
on the souls of the faithful departed.
Have mercy on the souls
of the faithful departed.
Thou who holdest
the keys to death and to Hell…
we ask for your mercy,
We didn't free ourselves of anything,
José Arcadio Buendía.
We ended up raising a monster.
Attack now!
BASED ON THE NOVEL BY
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ